let's start with the first one the first
in first out algorithm so this is simple as the
name
suggests if all the frames are used then
you free the one that contains the page that
was loaded more time ago so here we have
our reference string let's say we have 3 frames
in total for the process so we can only load
up to three pages at a time for the process
let's go through the example it's simple so
we start here
initially all the frames are free we didn't
load anything yet
so we need page 7 is it in one of the frames?
no then we have one page fault and we put
seven here then we need zero do we have it?
no two page faults and we store 0 and then
we go for one
which results in the third
page fault and we store 1 now we need page
2 we are here so we ask ourselves is it there?
no we have a free frame? in this case the answer
is no so in that case we need to substitute
the page that was loaded more time ago this
case would be 7
so we have one page fault and now 2 will be placed
in the position where we had 7 now we need
zero it's there so it's fine
an so on and so forth so if you do the entire
if you go through the entire reference string
you will see that at the end we will have
15 page faults
of course we change the reference string
you will get a different number of page faults
something that is interesting about this algorithm
is that it can suffer for this from this anomaly
the Belady's anomaly which basically means
that actually having more frames might result
in having more page faults the global tendency
is the same the more frames you have the better
but for specific changes going from n to n plus
one frames might actually increase the number
of page faults
and it's simple to implement because you basically
use a FIFO queue and then you always take the
oldest you had in this first in first out
queue to select which is the victim frame if you
need to
swap out a page
and this is an example of these Belady's
anomaly and you can try it out by yourself
so you see that the tendency is it goes down
but actually there can be some spikes here
so when you go from 3 to 4 frames actually
you might experience more page faults than in this
case when you add less frames which with
3 will be 9 in this example
no one can ask ok we got 15 page faults
with a FIFO algorithm what is the optimal?
what is the actual minimum number of page
faults we can get? well it turns out that
there is an optimal algorithm and the idea is
simple if you have to replace a page then
you should replace the one that will not be
used for the longest period of time
and if you do this for our reference string
you will see that 9
is the lowest number of page faults you can
get for this reference string if you have
frames that you can use for the process
now the problem is that you cannot really
implement the optimal algorithm because in
practice you don't know which will be the
page that will not be used for the longest
period of time knowing that would basically mean
know/reading the future for generic processing
a generic execution with many other processes
but still you can use it at least as a means
to understand how close you get with your
algorithm to the optimal number so you see
that 15 versus 9 is actually not that good
this is just the execution you can try it
out by yourself and you see that nine it's
the total number of page faults we would get
in this case
an algorithm that is used in practice that
gets closer to the optimal one is the
least recently used so when you have to select
a victim frame instead of picking the one
that will not be used for the longest period
of time you pick the one that has not been
used for the longest period of time the idea
is that more or less this should be the same
if it is a lot of time I'm not using a certain
frame then most likely I will also not really
use it a lot in the future
and this connects back to the concept of locality
we already mentioned before
so this is what I just said you replace the
page that has not been used in the most amount
of time looking of course at the past not
the future
so you can keep track of the time at
which you access each page and then when you
have to select the victim frame you pick the
one that was not accessed for the longest
time so let's try to look here for example
here you need page 2 you need to select a
victim frame so which one do you pick here?
well the one that you have used
that you have not been using sorry in the longest
amount of time in this case it would be 7 so
you pick seven you can try this example
try please all these examples by yourself
and check that
your numbers match with these ones and here you
can see that you end up with 12 faults at
the end of the day which means in this case
it's performing better than the first in first
out algorithm now there are different ways
in which you can implement this
again as always different implementations
means different tradeoffs different costs
you can go with a counter implementation
so basically you keep the value of the clock
one for each page and you update it whenever
you access the page when you have to select
which is the victim frame you take the one
with the lowest value for the clock that is
the oldest one
problem of this is pretty simple but you need
to search through all the table to keep track
to find what is the smallest clock value because
the table is not necessarily sorted on
the clock values so to update the table
it's O(1) time it you just store the value
of the clock but to find the victim frame
its O(n) where n is the size of the page table
otherwise you can keep an additional data
structure in this case a stack
and whenever you reference a page you go
in the stack you find where that page is and
you move it to the top in this case updating
each entry takes a bit more because we have
to search inside the stack and put it up put
the entry up at the top but on the other hand
we have to find the victim frame that becomes
O(1) time is fast because you know that what
you have at the bottom of the stack is the
page that you did not use for the longest
amount of time
this is just an example so if you are before
here 7
this is the situation with the stack you see
that two it's on top because you just
used it and 4 it's at the bottom because
it's the one that has not been used for the
longest period of time now if you want to
access 7
you do that you have it already but then
you pick it and you move it up to the top and
you see at the bottom if you want to know
which is the victim frame to choose
when you need that it's the one that is at
the end at the
bottom of the stack
you can also write approximate versions of
this
algorithm one is to use simply a reference
bit when you load the page that is zero and
when you reference the page the bit is set
to 1 now
you only have two values zero and one so it's
not really accurate it's a very coarse grained
approximation but if you have to select a
bit in frame you can select one that has bit
0 because you know that at least the ones
with bit 0 have been
used before the ones that have bit one
alternatively you can go for the second chance
alright here we have a description but
I think it's easier if I just show you how
it works so basically you have an extra bit
for each entry and you keep a circular queue
of the pages
so let's say that this is the page you are
currently pointing out as the next victim
if you see one then you don't pick this as
a victim but you set it to zero and you move to
the next one so you keep moving until you
find one that has 0
as soon as you find 0 then that is the victim
frame so what is happening here is that
if this is one it means that this page has
been used you put this to zero before moving
to the next page
which means you are giving a second chance
to that page
to be not selected as a victim frame because
it will keep looking at the other pages if
all the other pages have also the reference
bit set to 1 then you will get back to this
page an if it is still zero it means well
then it's not really being used so I will
select it as a victim frame if it went back
to one cause the process was actually using
the page then it will get again a second chance
before being selected this is why it's called
second-chance page replacement algorithm